MAN: (SINGING) MTV...
NARRATOR: Previously on 1923...
You have been tasked
to bring justice to a murderer!
But the murderer is you.
-(GUN FIRES)
(GRUNTS)
Life hasn't shown me many reasons
to keep fighting for it.
If you don't live.
someday they won't remember
we were even here.
-(GUN FIRES)
(GRUNTS)
(TEONNA AND FATHER RENAUD SCREAM)
We journey the path of the pioneers
in the name of lost love
soon to be found.
Hillary. where did he...
(GASPING)
Spencer's coming home.
BANNER: Get to the train station.
If this Spencer Dutton steps off.
put a hole in him.
After you've killed the nephew.
we kill the whole lot of 'em.
Bring him home.
ALEC: Everyone acts
like he's something special.
With a gun in his hand.
there's no one better.
You don't say.
(GUN FIRES)
(OPENING THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
You'd be a lot more
comfortable inside.
Can't stand that house
when my husband isn't in it.
It's just a big log prison
for my worries.
Understood.
Okay.
I'd feel more comfortable
if you sat inside.
Don't fret. Zane.
I'm still spry enough to run inside
if the bullets start flying.
(CHUCKLES)
He'll arrive today. I reckon.
I've done the math.
Sioux Falls to Rapid City.
Rapid City to Deadwood.
Sheridan. and Billings.
And then home...
Then the fight.
Well. anything worth having
is worth fighting for. Zane.
They don't make women
like you anymore. ma'am.
Yes. they do.
It's the men they make different.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
(DOOR OPENS. CLOSES)
He never came home.
Jack. He never came home.
Sit.
He went to town to meet
his uncle on the train.
Felt Jacob was too shorthanded.
Was he? I don't know.
He's lived to be 80
judging such things.
Don't know why a 25-year-old
would think he knows any better.
That's the boy in him. Elizabeth.
But he's a married man now.
He doesn't get to make decisions
about his life without asking.
Because the consequences
of those decisions
affect more than just him.
I just pray he's learned that lesson
before it's burned into you. my dear.
Now get inside
before you catch your death.
Death is the only thing
you can catch out here.
(DOOR OPENS. CLOSES)
(SIGHS) Thank you.
Who are those guys?
We hired 'em in the fall.
More badges in town
while you healed up
from being shot to shit.
I don't know 'em.
Interviewed 'em with your wife.
They seemed fine.
One of them was a cop in Chicago.
Irish?
Think so. I don't know.
They all sound the same to me.
Banner? When did you get home?
I don't know. I was late.
Why are you sitting in the dark?
-I'm not a good man. Ellie.
-Banner.
You've been as good as one can be
with the options you've had.
I don't think I'm a bad man either.
There are takers in this world
and those who get took.
I just got fed up with being took.
But I'm not evil.
... I take no pleasure
in another man's pain.
They pay a man $20 a day to work
the fishing trawlers out of Portland.
You earn more than that here.
I make it.
I don't earn it.
Dutton has half this county.
half the next one.
No bigger taker in the state.
But the man ain't evil.
Whitfield's evil. Ellie.
Heart black as coal.
Dutton...
he takes.
He don't care if you suffer.
I understand that.
I respect it. even.
Whitfield takes to make you suffer.
It ain't the taking he wants.
It's the suffering.
I don't beat no women.
Use 'em up.
Kill 'em.
Throw 'em off a cliff
and go find another.
Banner.
What in the world
are you talking about?
(VOICE BREAKING) I'm a man.
Man's got to look his son in the eye.
Stand by what he did.
I can't do that here.
Not anymore.
Get packed.
We're leaving.
(SHIVERING)
(SCREAMS)
(PANTING RAGGEDLY)
(GASPING)
(PANTING)
(CRYING)
(GROANS)
(PANTING)
(GRUNTING)
(EXHALING SHARPLY)
(GASPS)
(PANTING)
(COUGHING. RASPING)
(GRUNTS)
(SHIVERING)
(COUGHS)
(GASPING)
(PANTING)
(MUTTERS INDISTINCTLY)
(GRUNTING)
(CONTINUES PANTING)
(PANTING)
Ever seen anything like that?
Water from the ceiling?
Corn prices.
wheat prices. whole hogs.
cattle yields.
The newspaper of the West
IS a commodity report
and a rumor mill.
I long for the London Times.
We live on an island
of mountains. girls.
Surrounded by an ocean of prairie.
completely cut off
from the electricity of culture
and thoughtful exchange.
But all that changes today.
Why today?
Because today
the present becomes the past
and the future becomes the present.
(LAUGHS)
(TAPS TABLE)
Our little sparrow...
seems worried a cat's lurking about.
He's talking to you.
Enjoy the evening?
Parts of it.
Ah. parts.
And other parts?
I did not.
But you see.
the parts you wish would end
magnify the pleasure.
The pain is only for reference.
(DOOR CLOSES)
(SHUDDERING)
(PANTING)
(MOANING SOFTLY)
LINDY: Yeah.
(SCREAMING)
(GROANING)
Lay on the table. Mabel.
-That rhymes.
-(LAUGHING) It certainly does.
Lay on the table.
(PANTING)
(DISHES CLATTERING)
(MABEL YELLS)
(FLIES BUZZING)
Hmm.
Can't say he didn't deserve it.
Men like him beg the world to do it.
The world usually obliges.
MAMIE: What do you think?
Ran up on this boy. they shot it out?
Two different boots.
No boots.
No exit from bullet.
Was a pistol.
Boy had a rifle.
You think this girl...
Priest.
That is the priest's boot.
You think a priest killed him?
I think a priest killed him.
Priest.
We waiting for a signal?
No signal.
Just start killing. then.
Just start killing.
(SIGHS)
2:20 arrival.
Anybody else know that?
Well. it ain't no secret. Jacob.
and it damn sure won't be
as soon as the ticket agent
shouts it out.
-Filling up in there?
-Starting to.
Any strange faces I should know about?
It's a train station. Jacob.
All the faces are strange.
-(DOOR OPENS)
-(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(SIGHS)
Everyone looks like travelers.
Everyone so far.
Yeah.
Not everyone.
Three first class to Portland.
Sleeper car?
Shared?
First class. I said.
That's $67.
You don't think I have it.
I love being judged
by half a man as me.
Prepay the meals. sir?
We'll pay as we dine.
Train arrives at 2:20.
Departs at 2:45.
I advise being
on the platform at 1:50.
-If it arrives early...
-(STAMPS TICKET)
-...it leaves early.
-We'll wait.
We're not going anywhere.
Take a seat.
I'll be along.
I've seen some cowardly
camouflage in my life...
but I don't think I've seen this.
I'm taking my family and I'm leaving.
Had enough of this place.
You're under indictment. Banner.
you can't go anywhere.
I can't leave the country.
The judge said nothing
about leaving the state.
So I suppose it's a coincidence
that you picked
this particular day to leave.
You mean the same day
as your nephew arrives?
The great hope?
Maybe he is.
Good for you.
You get to keep your land
for a generation or two.
Whitfield's just the first. you know?
There's more where he came from.
More of them than me.
And way more than you.
They'll never let him leave
this station. Jacob.
You can take my word for it
or you can learn it.
Let 'em try.
And you can try and get on that train.
but that ain't gonna happen either.
You started this thing. Banner.
You don't get to leave it.
I've got a son. Jacob.
What have I been teaching him?
Just so long as they get to leave.
Can you give me that?
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
Yeah.
I can give you that.
They won't be just here. Jacob.
Do you know what I mean?
Yeah.
I know what you mean.
Give me your bundle.
Just here.
That bag never leaves your sight.
Everything okay?
It will be.
There's gonna be chaos
on that platform. Ellie.
People running and screaming.
And we are gonna walk through it
like we're headed to church
and get on that train.
Don't look up.
Don't look anybody in the eye.
Just walk.
Do you understand?
I think so.
Mom. buffalo!
I heard you the first time. Tucker.
The whole train heard you.
They've got you outnumbered.
They sure do.
Where are we?
Montana.
Thought all the buffalo were gone.
Not all of 'em.
There's still some here.
Some in. uh. Wind Rivers. I hear.
Yellowstone has a pretty big herd.
You ever hear of Little Bighorn?
See right out there?
Lakota called it
the Battle of the Greasy Grass.
Grass here is so rich in protein.
it feel like grease.
Worst defeat
in American military history.
Wait. Custer lost?
You can't lose any worse.
That's not what they said in school.
They said Custer was a hero.
That's 'cause schools
don't teach you what happened.
They teach you
what they want you to believe.
And they can teach you that.
you'll believe anything they tell you.
What's that?
A lion's tooth.
There's no lions here.
That's 'cause it's not from here.
it's from Africa.
Want to trade?
Trade what?
That's a nice knife.
Guy I traded for it says
it's from the revolution.
The war.
Our teachers said we won that one.
You and I are living proof of that.
Are you sure your mother would be okay
with you trading this away?
(WHISPERS) She don't know I have it.
See. I don't know. I was. um...
I was planning on giving this
to my son one day.
What's his name?
I don't know.
Haven't met him yet.
Don't think you meet him.
I think you got to make him.
All right. Tucker. that's enough.
Stop bothering the man.
No. no. It's no bother.
What do you say?
I don't know. (SIGHS)
Please. Disarm the child.
You got a deal.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
That's a good trade.
You got suckered.
Know how many pocket knives
there are in the world?
I bet this is the only lion's tooth
in the whole country.
Yeah. you may be right.
This keeps getting more interesting.
Shot in his sleep.
-Shot by who?
-Don't know.
Priest maybe.
Face is burned.
Then stabbed.
Stabbed. then shot.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
He ran out.
So the girl did this.
Didn't do that.
But she did this.
Quite the coyote. this girl.
These men. they talk
of this girl killing everywhere.
but it was the men killing in Oklahoma
and the men who killed here.
I don't think the girl is the problem.
I think that's the problem.
And the problem is gone.
Be that as it may. we have a warrant.
We have a duty to serve it.
A warrant from a judge we don't know
in a territory we don't serve.
We didn't ride out here to find
a girl. we rode out here to find them.
And we found 'em.
And good riddance.
She's above us on the ridge.
-(HORSE NEIGHING)
(GRUNTING)
Ride around her to the east!
She drew her pistol!
Marshal. do not shoot!
(YELLS)
-Marshal. do not fire!
-She's fired at us!
-(TEONNA SCREAMS)
-(HORSE NEIGHS)
(GROANS)
-(GUN FIRES)
(GRUNTS)
(GUN CLICKING)
(TEONNA SHOUTS)
(PANTING)
MAMIE: You'll be dead
before it reaches your shoulder.
Seems a silly death for one
who's fought so hard to avoid it.
Better than your noose.
Quicker. no doubt.
(PANTING)
And I've lived in your prisons.
I won't do it again.
I don't choose who gets
the noose or who goes to prison.
That's for a judge to decide.
If you're innocent.
he'll give you a chance to prove it.
Prove how?
Through testimony.
Through witnesses.
What witnesses?
The nuns who raped me?
The priests who beat me
and put me in an oven to cook
because I don't know how to make soap?
Won't eat maggots.
Won't let them put
their fingers inside me.
(PANTING)
And who speaks for me?
Which relative
will they dig from their grave
to speak for me?
What is she talking about?
The Indian schools.
I know those schools.
Know those priests.
I don't know her path.
But I know that path.
(GUN COCKS)
They lied?
You never killed?
The one who beat me I killed.
And the one who raped me I killed.
Then I killed the one
who murdered my cousin.
Tried to murder me.
Then the priest.
(EXHALES)
Yes.
I've killed.
I'd say.
What about him?
Badge and boots.
(PANTING)
(WIND WHISTLING SOFTLY)
(GROANS) I've been shot.
You ain't been shot. You been woke up.
Now stay that way.
You son of a bitch.
I'm gonna box you silly
-when we get back...
-(GUN FIRES)
(GUNS FIRING)
(EXHALES)
(HORSE NEIGHS)
(MUFFLED POPPING)
(DISTANT GUNFIRE)
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES)
-They're coming.
-CARA: Yes.
I know. Take that shotgun.
Get in the conversation pit.
Stay away from the windows. get low.
Under the table.
They're here.
There's a whole lot of 'em.
Zane! What do I do?
You get up high. give us cover.
and use Jacob's elk rifle.
Stay there. you hear me?
Don't shoot me!
Where's Sam?
How many is there?
Don't know. A bunch.
Let 'em get close.
shoot into the cabs.
shoot the drivers.
then we get back to the house
and we fight 'em from there.
Steady. Not yet.
Not yet.
-They're almost on top of us.
-Not yet!
Jasper. you take the lead car.
Randy. you get the second car.
Dennis the third. I get the last.
Get ready.
-Kill 'em.
-(GUNS FIRING)
Dennis. you and Randy
get to the house and get on the roof!
Two can't hold 'em.
Ain't trying to hold 'em.
just trying to slow 'em down.
Go!
(GUNFIRE IN DISTANCE)
What can I do?
You can hide in the basement
with your children. ma'am.
Ma'am. go find your children!
You too. ma'am.
I'm staying here.
Go to the basement!
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES)
(SHORT WHISTLE)
Lord. help us.
Of all the things
I've had to do for this ranch...
this takes the cake.
Takes the bloody cake.
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
(BELL RINGING)
Twenty-five minute alert for 2:20
from Sheridan. Deadwood.
Pierre. Sioux Falls.
(EXHALES)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(COUGHS)
They're here.
-How many?
-About a dozen.
Plus Banner.
Plus whoever
we haven't picked out yet.
Better get Livingston Police out here.
There's only three.
and they ain't worth a shit.
Well. that's better than nothing.
We're gonna stop it
before it comes to that.
This is the only way we stop them.
HENRY: What's in Portland?
Your future.
I don't have one here?
A man can't get rich in Montana.
He gets rich somewhere else.
Then he comes to Montana.
And he gets even richer.
(SNIFFLING)
I'm sorry. Spencer.
(SOBBING)
This is your plan?
(CRYING) This is your plan for us?
Let us know love.
then rip it from us...
(CRYING)
...then give us a child...
then drag me through hell...
to freeze here?
Hours from him?
What kind of God does that?
(RAGGED BREATHING)
(TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWING IN DISTANCE)
(PANTING)
(TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWING)
(GRUNTING)
Stop!
Livingston.
This is Seven Pierre 91.
Please!
Please. stop!
(FAINTLY) Please! Stop!
Alex?
(SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
Sir?
-(GRUNTS)
-(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(SOBBING)
(PASSENGERS MURMURING)
(PASSENGERS EXCLAIMING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(MOANING. CRYING)
SPENCER: Alex!
(SOBBING)
Alex!
Spencer?
Spencer!
(ALEX PANTING)
Alex!
(LAUGHS. SOBS)
(CRYING)
(SOBBING)
(CRYING QUIETS)
(SNIFFLES)
What...
What are you...
You sent smoke signals to my train.
You leapt from the train?
I leapt from the train.
Did you. by chance.
ask the train to wait for us?
No. it slipped my mind.
So. train is continuing
in the opposite direction.
Yeah. that's a pretty good guess.
Ah. Well...
so good of you
to join me in this pickle.
Free from the burden of a solution.
I don't know what that means.
It's an insult. my love.
(SOFT CHUCKLE)
I have a solution.
(STAMMERS) I'm all ears.
Big Timber's three miles from here.
I'm gonna carry you.
Carry me? (CHUCKLES)
I've carried an elk quarter farther.
I don't know what an elk quarter is.
but I assume very heavy
and a testament to your swarthiness.
(SIGHS) Heavier than you.
but not by much.
You've eaten well
on this journey. my love.
You may carry me
from certain death. sir.
but you may not joke
about my weight while doing it.
Hmm.
It's your fault. you know.
My fault?
I suppose he'll be tall like you.
(SPENCER PANTING)
(ALEX CHUCKLES)
(CHUCKLES)
-Ow.
-I know. I know.
-I know.
-(PANTING)
(TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWING IN DISTANCE)
(GRUNTING)
(ALEX SHUDDERING)
(LABORED BREATHING)
This is a doctor traveling
in first class.
My name is Andrew.
Open your mouth for me. please.
(MUFFLED GROANING)
I need warm water and towels.
lots of it. fast.
I need everyone to clear the room.
please. And close the door.
There isn't much medical research
on cold as a clinical condition.
but in the army we saw plenty.
and what we learned is.
if you get cold fast. you warm fast.
if you get cold slow.
you must warm yourself slowly.
How long were you exposed
to the elements?
I think... about a... A day or two?
These clothes are as cold as she is.
We need to get them off. I apologize.
There's no time for modesty.
(GRUNTING)
-(PANTING)
-HENDERSON: There you go.
(ALEX SHUDDERS)
What do we do about the shivers?
The shiver is good.
It's her body trying to warm.
Was she shivering when you found her?
Was she disoriented?
-Disoriented how?
-Saying things
that are illogical
or don't make sense.
Oh. she does that anyway.
I can hear you.
Is there any other symptoms?
Her temperature is 94.2 degrees.
She was minutes away
from death when you found her.
(KNOCKING AT DOOR)
(ALEX CONTINUES SHIVERING)
(GRUNTING)
Press that tight against her.
(SHUDDERING)
HENDERSON: All over. sir.
don't be bashful.
(LAUGHS) He has flaws.
but bashful isn't one of them.
HENDERSON: Have you two met?
My... husband. sir.
It's a long story.
One worth hearing. no doubt.
Put this under her arms.
(PANTING)
(CONTINUES SHIVERING)
You must tell us when the towels cool
SO we may replace them.
How many months?
(STAMMERING)
Six.
Will... Will he survive?
We'll see.
The female form is a miracle
that can withstand
physical hardships well beyond
that of men...
especially when with child.
If there is a way
to protect the child.
your body will find it.
I'll be right back.
My... body's a miracle.
Hear that? (CHUCKLES)
-I already knew that.
-Hmm.
(BREATHING SHAKILY)
I never thought I'd see you again.
You didn't have
to go through all this.
I was coming for you.
Couldn't take the chance.
If you found someone else.
how could I kill her from England?
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
That rarest of creatures.
Your smile.
HENDERSON: I want you
to sit up and drink this.
Slowly.
(GRUNTING)
(PANTING)
HENDERSON: Slow.
It's likely she's dehydrated
on top of everything else.
Don't get off in Livingston.
Engine man has radioed
the station in Bozeman.
An ambulance is waiting.
They'll take you to the hospital
where they have seen far more ailments
from the cold than I have.
Let's change out these towels.
(GUNS FIRING)
MAN: Retreat!
Let's get on the roof.
(DOOR CLOSES)
See where they went?
Just down the hill. They're not
going anywhere till tonight.
I think that's their plan.
Jacob should be back by then
with the sheriff
and everybody else.
We don't know what they ran into.
They could be in the same boat.
We need someone in the house
with the women.
You're the one with a wife
in there. We got the roof.
Be safe.
(SIGHS)
And here I thought it was
them boys on the roof
-making lucky shots.
-It was me with the luck.
Though this contraption takes
most of the luck out of it.
They're gonna wait till night.
My guess is try to burn us out.
How do we fight that?
Well. we got a full moon in our favor.
Just need them clouds to break.
So. we need God to do his part.
-(LAUGHS)
-We need wind.
I don't care who does
their part to send it.
That would be God.
I'll ask.
If they do get in the house. Cara...
Just pray for wind and a bright moon.
I'll ask for wind.
I'll pray my husband comes
and brings Spencer with him.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
It's late.
Yep.
(TRAIN CHUGGING IN DISTANCE)
Here she comes.
06.8.
(GRUNTS. LAUGHS)
-Alex. what?
-Feeling is coming back to her feet.
(GROANS) That's a new sensation.
(COUGHS)
(PANTING)
Are we there?
Close. It's another 30 miles or so.
(TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWS)
(TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWING)
Remember what I said.
Ignore the chaos. get on the train.
Where are you going?
There's enough money
in your bag to start over.
-Start clean.
-Start...
What are you talking about?
What's happening?
Trust me.
(TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWS)
MAN: Clear away!
Clear away for passengers
to disembark.
(BELL CLANGING)
(GRUNTING)
(BRAKES SCREECHING)
(STEAM HISSING)
-Spencer?
-Sir. what are you doing?
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Drop it!
-(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
-Drop it now!
-You drop it.
-Drop it!
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
JACOB: Put that gun down.
for God's sakes!
Drop it! Drop them!
-(GUNS FIRING)
-(GLASS SHATTERING)
(WOMEN SCREAMING)
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
Henry.
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES)
-(ELLIE YELLS)
-Ellie!
Get on the train!
(GRUNTS)
(MUFFLED SCREAMS)
So you're a man of your word
after all.
I told you.
Get my family to Portland.
Where they're clean of this.
Clean of me.
You have my word.
It's all a man's got.
What was this?
Fear. I suppose. Arrogance.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Dear God.
You're shot. sir.
Old leaks. I think.
HENDERSON: Looks fresh to me.
Bill! Can you walk?
-Haven't tried.
-JACOB: Carl!
Give him a hand.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
HENDERSON: I urge you.
take this train to Bozeman.
There is an ambulance waiting.
-Arrange more...
-We need to load passengers.
-Come back for them.
-It's not as easy as...
Come back for them!
This fight ain't over.
And I ain't got
that much fight left in me.
I need to get my wife to a hospital.
(PANTING)
I'll head home once she's there.
You might not have a home by then.
Come with me.
SPENCER: This is my uncle.
(DOOR CLOSES)
(SOFTLY) Jacob.
Ma'am.
War isn't a metaphor in this family.
I'm discovering.
It is not.
ALEX: Time to fight yours.
I suppose.
If we want a life here. it is.
But we can build a life anywhere.
ALEX: This is why she wrote you.
War is what you came home for.
I love you.
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
(DOOR OPENS)
I'll meet you in Bozeman.
(DOOR CLOSES)
Let's take a look at these wounds.
I got a funny feeling...
you got quite a story to tell.
Yes. (LAUGHS)
(QUIET MURMURING)
I could use that.
I need to deputize you.
Taking cars or horses?
Got both. Cars are faster.
ELSA: In her heart. she feared
she'd never see him again.
But she saw him.
Tasted him one last time.
For her. that was enough.
Ought to trade that out for a shotgun.
Tricky to shoot around corners
with an elephant gun.
Don't shoot around corners
with this one.
You shoot through them.
(ENGINE STARTS)
(GUNS FIRING)
CARA: Come on.
Show yourself.
(GRUNTS)
(DISTANT GUNFIRE)
(GRUNTING)
(BULLETS RICOCHETING)
(ELIZABETH SCREAMS)
(PANTING)
(GRUNTS)
(GUN COCKS)
(PANTING)
(GRUNTS)
-(SCREAMS)
-(GUN FIRES)
(PANTING)
(GASPS. PANTING)
Told you not to stay there.
Pretty glad you did.
But don't do it no more. Get upstairs.
Today is the dawn
of Montana's own Gilded Age.
Today. we begin extracting
the only resource
which increases in value
the more common it becomes...
tourism.
As farmers abandon the field
for the comfort
and opportunities of the city.
the wilds of America
will become parks.
Playgrounds for the elite.
Let's say they come.
How do we profit? Hotels?
-Yes.
-Restaurants?
-Absolutely.
-And this resort.
the ski resort?
I'm in the final negotiations
on that property as we speak.
Inns and cafés
are notoriously poor business models.
and frankly. sir. beneath you.
-Beneath all of us.
-WHITFIELD: You are correct.
Independently.
But combined.
one place where every whim
of the patron is met.
Lodging. dining. liquor. dancing.
gambling. skiing. hunting.
All of them.
including transportation
here and home. provided by us.
What about competition?
Our competition is Colorado.
Another 600 miles away.
Cities give one culture. convenience.
but they rob man
of the thing that makes him man.
his insatiable. inexplicable need
to traverse untamed land.
Battle its monsters.
overcome its mountains.
No concert in Manhattan can compare.
When you bed a woman.
it is the animal in you doing it.
That animal needs to wander.
We will give it the chance.
-Hear. hear!
-(OVERLAPPING CHATTER)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
I'll ride with her.
-We have an ambulance over here for...
-I said I'm gonna ride with her.
-This one's full. sir. Take another.
-I'll ride in the back.
I ride in the back.
Not tonight.
(SHUDDERING)
How far to the hospital?
Five or six miles.
Would you mind checking
that we have sufficient fuel
for such a journey?
We're not gonna run out of gas.
I've never heard a woman
ask that question before.
(LAUGHS SOFTLY) Well...
Once bitten. twice shy. Jacob.
(SOFTLY) Yeah.
SPENCER: Stop the car.
Turn off the engine.
(ENGINE TURNS OFF)
(DISTANT GUNFIRE)
That's coming from up at the house.
Sounds like it.
Turn off your headlights.
Drive us up the road.
Damn it! They're gonna need us inside!
-That ain't all of them!
-Stay on the roof.
Keep shooting.
(GRUNTS)
(WHISPERING) Cara.
They're right outside the house.
Damn this man.
(EXHALES)
Wait.
Stop the car.
It's Spencer.
Ma'am?
Spencer's here.
(GROANS)
(GRUNTS)
(YELPS)
(MAN GRUNTS)
Aunt Cara?
CARA: Spencer?
So you know. I'm right over here.
I see you. You shot?
No more than anyone else.
(GASPING) Oh.
Oh...
Dang it. Spencer.
I didn't even get to fire a shot.
-Where's Jacob?
-SPENCER: He's at the hospital.
With my wife.
You... You have a wife?
Boy. do I.
I'm in her debt.
Not there for Jacob.
She's got her own problems.
I'll ready the carriage.
We have cars. ma'am.
I don't see him.
Where is he?
-Where's Jack?
-I don't know.
Ma'am. we haven't seen him.
Dennis. take Jasper.
ride the road to Livingston.
Find my boy.
Yes. ma'am.
Which one's the leader?
The leader sits in a mansion.
Destroying lives while getting fat
and throwing dinner parties
for the men
who will carve this place to pieces.
He did this?
Most certainly.
What's his name?
Whitfield.
Can't seem to... find the bullet.
Can't find the bullet. you idiot.
'cause there is no bullet.
It's an old wound.
If the lead is inside you.
it can poison you slowly.
Do you think I care
about the slow ones?
I'm 80 fucking years old.
Sew it up!
(DISTANT GROANING)
(ALEX MOANING)
(PANTING)
SURGEON: She's dilated
over eight centimeters.
Her body's terminating the pregnancy.
We should abort and amputate.
You will do nothing of the sort.
Miss. the baby is six months. if that.
It can't survive outside the womb.
Your legs are necrotic to the shin.
Your left hand is necrotic
above the wrist.
You will not see tomorrow's sunset
if we don't amputate immediately.
-(GRUNTING)
-She's crowning.
Let's get this over with.
then move her to surgery.
(STRAINING)
(PANTING)
Bring him to me.
Why are you so confident it's a boy?
Because I know.
Your guess is correct.
Miss. it's best not
to become attached.
Its lungs are not developed
enough to survive the hour.
-much less...
-(BABY CRYING)
(LAUGHS SOFTLY)
So be it.
Give me the hour.
I need you prepped for surgery.
Give her the goddamn baby.
(CRYING)
(SOFTLY) Hi.
(BABY CRIES QUIETLY)
(SHUSHING QUIETLY)
(ALEX SOBS SOFTLY)
No crueler thing than hope.
Let's prep her for surgery.
No.
She said no.
She will die.
and the baby will die.
She can make more children.
She said no.
I'll send a priest.
I don't need one of those. either.
(DOOR OPENS)
-(DOOR CLOSES)
(EXHALES)
I'm going to name him John.
After his brother.
He'd like that.
But...
he'd like a world
you're still in more.
The mother that would choose
herself over her child...
is no mother at all.
How can I raise a child with...
stubs for feet
and clubs for hands?
Then there's two children.
This is a conversation you
should have with your husband.
I think all our conversations
are over.
They were splendid.
In truth. I did most of the talking.
You tell him why for me.
You tell him yourself.
Well. that's the plan. but...
You can see how well
my plans are working out.
You will tell him yourself.
(SNIFFLES)
JASPER: But his horse
was loose at the house.
No saddle.
Maybe he took a different horse.
his got loose.
We need to go back for the wagon.
This one?
She's in there.
(ALEX GRUNTS SOFTLY)
(ALEX WHISPERING)
They wanted to take my legs and...
...and my hand.
(ALEX SNIFFLES)
And take our baby...
(EXHALES)
...throw them all away
like... rubbish.
I said no.
I can see that.
Your legs are a long way
from your heart.
I'm not a dreamer.
I don't imagine
running through fields.
I have to do it.
And I would never trade...
what we made...
for me.
Be patient with him. Spencer.
If he's anything like me...
he'll be a terrible child.
(CRYING)
(RAGGED BREATHING)
I wish I could have met her.
JACOB: Hmm.
You would have liked her.
Mustang wild.
Like somebody else I know.
Now you're talking about
yourself again.
Go to the sale barn.
We need two milk goats.
Barn ain't open.
Well. when it does.
you'll be first in line.
And make sure they're producing now.
Milk next week does us no good.
Do you think I... I could just...
(SIGHS) I'm sure
they wouldn't mind. honey.
Perhaps tomorrow.
(JACOB SIGHS)
SPENCER: Cara?
I don't know what to do.
You're not supposed to. my dear.
But I do.
Let's go.
I want to meet the man
who killed my wife.
What business do you have here...
Lindy?
We talked about this.
Sorry. Sometimes
I just get carried away.
(CHUCKLES)
Self-control. Lindy.
-is the cornerstone...
-(DOOR OPENS)
(SCREAMS)
(YELLS)
(MABEL GASPING)
Look at me. You like it here?
-Then I think you should leave.
-(WHITFIELD GROANING)
JACOB: What did I tell you?
Now I understand.
The prodigal son has returned.
Mmm-hmm. And he will be
the last thing you ever see.
I suppose you've a plan for explaining
the murder of a man
in his dining room.
I think we about killed everybody
we'd have to explain it to.
WHITFIELD: You took an oath.
That badge came with an oath.
To uphold the law.
The law.
So be it.
To jail we go.
(GROANS)
I didn't say stand.
You can't get away with this.
JACOB: I don't plan to.
I plan on making such an example
of you that it'll be 50 years
before one of your kind
dares enter this valley again.
I want them teaching about
how you died in schoolbooks.
Look at me.
You killed my wife.
I don't know you.
Her name was Alex.
And I would really like
to hear you say it.
Alex?
(DOOR CLOSES)
Next before the court.
United States v. TEONNA Rainwater.
Three counts of murder
at the Indian School in North Dakota.
Why is this girl in my court
and not before
the North Dakota magistrate?
We spoke with the magistrate
in North Dakota
and he stated
all witnesses in this case
were in the Oklahoma territory.
thus making it more expedient
for the trial be held here.
Are these witnesses present?
If it please the court...
...these are death certificates
for the witnesses.
A Father Jaques RENAUD...
and U.S. Deputy Marshal Nathan Kent.
So?
Is she charged
with those deaths as well?
No. Your Honor.
Their deaths are unrelated.
We have U.S. Marshal Fossett
prepared to testify to the specifics
of the witnesses' deaths.
If it please the court.
READING: What would please the court
are witnesses to support
a murder charge.
Does prosecution have witnesses??
We do not. Your Honor.
Do you have evidence
that ties the defendant
to these allegations?
We do not. Your Honor.
Then what are we...
Why are we discussing this?
Prosecution would like
to submit a motion to dismiss.
READING: Please.
Motion granted.
And let's make certain
the North Dakota magistrate
keep its business
in North Dakota where it belongs.
Especially if this is how
they conduct it.
(DOOR OPENS)
(DOOR CLOSES)
What does that mean?
Means you're free to go.
(PANTING)
(VEHICLE APPROACHES)
(HORN HONKS)
(CAR PASSES)
I'm not sure what to do.
Well. we'd sure like it
if you'd leave.
Go where?
How about home?
Not sure I have one.
Maybe it's time to find a new one.
For deer.
Right.
(SIGHS)
I'm not sure which way to go.
I hear California.
More Mexican and Indians than whites.
Fruit on the trees. game in the hills.
Land of the Chumash.
West.
If you're standing in the ocean.
you went too far.
Thank you.
TWO SPEARS: TEONNA!
You were right to fight back.
Maybe.
But it cost me everything.
Always does.
ELSA: It is likely there are
more unmarked graves in Montana
than those bestowed with marble
and inscriptions that tell
strangers who lay here.
Lovers need no marker.
They know exactly
where their soulmate rests.
Because they put them there.
CARA: Hmm.
I swear. boy. we'll need three goats
before June the way
you're guzzling it down.
(CHUCKLES)
(EXHALES)
CARA: I know.
Feels like you're quitting.
But you're not. child.
The reason for you being here is gone.
I hope you find another reason
in the city.
and it sweeps you off your feet.
and you write me stupid letters
about him. (CHUCKLES)
A man is the last thing on my mind.
Well. that's a good lesson
for all of us.
Never works out that way. though.
No. one always creeps in there
and muddles the senses.
Having your senses muddled
now and again.
it's not the worst thing. (CHUCKLES)
I'll write.
That'd be lovely.
Now. I must return my attention
to the future. here.
Because looking at you
is a window to the past.
And the past...
No matter
what life has in store for me.
I'll always love him.
You won't.
You'll love memories
until you make enough new ones.
And then one day.
you won't remember him at all.
And that's all right.
That's fine. that's life.
I'll remember him enough
for the both of us.
(JOHN FUSSES)
(CARA CHUCKLES)
(HORSES SNORTING SOFTLY)
There's wild cattle in the Crazies.
Rough mountains.
I'd rather gather 'em than buy 'em.
You coming?
You know. I think
I'm gonna sit on the porch.
stare at your son...
ponder the meaning of life.
Shit like that.
Be back in a week or so.
I have no doubt.
(CLICKS TONGUE)
(DOOR OPENS. CLOSES)
You're not on the gather.
Sitting this one out.
Retiring. are you?
I am.
So. what's the plan now?
Sit on the porch
and drink yourself silly
so I'm putting two babies
to bed each night? (CHUCKLES)
Something like that.
(CHUCKLES)
What was she like?
Alexandra.
If a shooting star could talk.
That's what she was like. honey.
Talking stars.
(CHUCKLING) Can you imagine?
Who'd have thought there'd be two?
ELSA: Spencer never remarried.
Took the comfort of a widow
and made another boy...
refused to marry her.
and one day. the widow was gone.
For Spencer. her memory didn't fade.
didn't fray at the edges
and didn't dull.
Not one.
Alexandra Dutton was born
on April Fool's Day. 1901.
in Oxfordshire. England.
And laid to rest March 29. 1924.
When old age
robbed him of his memories.
he simply closed his eyes
and dreamed up new ones.
And 45 years later.
my young brother joined her.
(ORCHESTRA PLAYING
UPBEAT INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC)
(CROWD CHATTERING)
Took you long enough.
(CLOSING THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
English - SDH